Guide to the Thomas Rain Crowe Papers, 1965-2020 RL.10018
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Thomas Rain Crowe papers
1950s-2020
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Crowe, Thomas Rain
RL.10018
106.8 Linear Feet
36.2 Gigabytes
Poet, essayist, translator, publisher, activist, and performing artist; owner and editor of New Native Press in Cullowhee (Jackson Co.), N.C. Crowe's collection contains correspondence with other writers, friends, and relatives; manuscript and printed versions of works by Crowe and others; poetry notebooks; publicity materials; photographs; audio cassettes and other media; New Native Press records; and other items. Other poets represented include Wendell Berry, Robert Bly, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Allen Ginsberg, Joy Harjo, David Meltzer, Philip Daughtry, Neeli Cherkovski, Gary Snyder, Bobi Jones (Welsh), Jack Hirschman, Ken Wainio, Dianna Henning, John Lane, and Joe Napora. There is documentation regarding Crowe's music, including collaborations with Nan Watkins. There is also material regarding San Francisco intellectual circles and the International Poetry Festival held there, as well as correspondence concerning activism regarding a wide range of political and social issues. Acquired as part of the George Washington Flowers Collection of Southern Americana.
Access Restrictions
Box AV 1, Box 3, and Box: Acc. 15/100: 1 are restricted because they contain audiovisual materials; these are closed until use copies can be made. Contact Research Services to request the production of use copies.
Original born-digital and electronic records are closed to use. Contact Research Services in advance to request reading room access to these items.
Provenance
The Thomas Rain Crowe Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase from 2000 to 2020.
Biographical and Historical Note
Thomas Rain Crowe is a poet, author, essayist, translator, publisher, activist, and performing artist. He is the founder of the New Native Press and Fern Hill Records, a record label devoted to poetry-music collaboration. Crowe is also a founding member of the spoken-word and music band The Boatrockers, and has authored 12 original and translated works. (Taken from NewNativePress.com.)
Collection Overview
Collection contains correspondence with other writers, friends, and relatives; manuscript and printed versions of works by Crowe and others; poetry notebooks; publicity materials; photographs; audio cassettes; New Native Press records; and other items. Figures represented include Wendell Berry, Robert Bly, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Allen Ginsberg, Joy Harjo, David Meltzer, Philip Daughtry, Neeli Cherkovski, Gary Snyder, Bobi Jones (Welsh), Jack Hirschman, Ken Wainio, Dianna Henning, John Lane, and Joe Napora. There is also material regarding San Francisco intellectual circles and the International Poetry Festival held there, as well as correspondence concerning activism regarding a wide range of political and social issues.
Unprocessed additions (from 2006 through 2019) have been described as individual series with box lists in the collection guide. Materials include New Native Press published books, original drafts and manuscripts, recordings, posters, book cover art and proofs, and galleys. Includes material related to the publication of Automatic Antiquity (Ken Wainio), Shaking the Grass for Dew (Richard Lewis), In the Middle Woods (Neeli Cherkovski), and rEdlipstick (Ted Pope). Also includes materials from various translations and anthologies featuring Crowe's edits and contributions; recent books by Crowe such as Zoro's Field: My Life in the Appalachian Woods, Crack Light, Rare Birds, The Watcher, A House of Girls, The End of Eden, Book of Rocks, The Brucciano Poemsarticles; interviews, appearances, and reviews by Crowe; documentation of Crowe's music with Thomas Rain Crowe and the Boatrockers; materials from Crowe's community and environmental activism in Tuckasegee, NC; color and black-and-white photographs; music, poetry, and video on audio cassettes, CDs, videocassettes, and computer diskettes or USBs.
Accession 2020-0069 is unprocessed; it includes correspondence, manuscript drafts, and personal and professional files related to Crowe's writing, editing, publishing, and activism.
Photographs; Small presses -- North Carolina; Poetry, Modern -- 20th century; American poetry -- 20th century; Poets, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; American poetry -- California -- San Francisco Bay Area; San Francisco Bay Area (Calif.) -- Intellectual life; Audio recordings.; Napora, Joe, 1944-; New Native Press; Snyder, Gary, 1930-; Wainio, Ken, 1952-2006; Henning, Dianna; Hirschman, Jack, 1933-; Jones, Bobi, 1929-; Lane, John; Crowe, Thomas Rain; Watkins, Nan
- Thomas Rain Crowe Papers, 1965-2000, 32 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Collection (2000-0178) (33,750 items, 45 lin. ft.; dated 1965-2000 and undated) contains correspondence with other writers, friends, and relatives; manuscript and printed versions of works by Crowe and others; poetry notebooks; publicity materials; photographs; audio cassettes; New Native Press records; and other items. Other poets represented include Gary Snyder, Bobi Jones (Welsh), Jack Hirschman, Ken Wainio, Dianna Henning, John Lane, and Joe Napora. There is also material regarding San Francisco intellectual circles and the International Poetry Festival held there, as well as correspondence concerning activism regarding a wide range of political and social issues. Acquired as part of the George Washington Flowers Collection of Southern Americana.
  - Correspondence
    - Steven W. Hawking (Box CO 1)
    - Gary Snyder (Box CO 1)
    - Robert Bly (Box CO 1)
    - Wendell Barry, R.S. Thomas, and Nancy Joyce Peters (Box CO 1)
    - James Laughlin (Box CO 1)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box CO 1)
    - Joy Harjo (Box CO 1)
    - Katuah "Feud" (Box CO 1)
    - Jim W. Miller (Box CO 1)
    - Fred Chappell (Box CO 1)
    - Coleman Barks (Box CO 1)
    - Kathryn Byer (Box CO 1)
    - Awiakta (Box CO 1)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 2 folders (Box CO 1)
    - Doreen Spark(?) (Box CO 1)
    - Gelolo McHugh (Box CO 1)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box CO 1)
    - Pancho Agula (Box CO 1)
    - Miscellaneous literary (Box CO 1)
    - Jack Hirschman (Box CO 2)
    - Ken Wainio, 2 folders (Box CO 2)
    - Kenn Long (Box CO 2)
    - Peter Blue Cloud (Box CO 2)
    - Bobi Jones/T. Crowe, 1993-1999 (Box CO 2)
    - Letters of reference for Crowe (for grants, etc.) (Box CO 3)
    - Richard Cambridge, 1999-2000 (Box CO 3)
    - Correspondence with group affiliated with "ecologian" Thomas Berry, 1980-1981 (Box CO 3)
    - John Lane, 1987-1999, 8 folders (Box CO 3)
    - Joe Napora, 1985, 1992-1999, 2 folders (Box CO 3)
    - Richard Cambridge, 1989-1999 (Box CO 3)
    - Dan Ladninsky, Hafiz translation-Penguin, 1999 (Box CO 3)
    - Evan Hundhausen-letters to a young poet (Box CO 3)
    - Bill Harlan-letters to a young writer (Box CO 3)
    - Letters from inmates in California prisons, 1975-1977 (Box CO 3)
    - Sharon Doubiago, 1979-1998 (Box CO 3)
    - Barbara-Ann Carver-Hunt, 1985-1997 (Box CO 3)
    - Jow Napora, 1985-1994, 3 folders (Box CO 4)
    - Larry Smith, 1997-1999 (Box CO 4)
    - Philip Daughtry, 1977-1997, 2 folders (Box CO 4)
    - Christopher Camuto, 1977-1997, 2 folders (Box CO 4)
    - Tim Buckley, 1985-1987 (Box CO 4)
    - Miscellaneous letters, 7 folders (Box CO 4)
    - Mindy Knott (Box CO 4)
    - Miscellaneous personal letters, 2 folders (Box CO 5)
    - Gil Ott (Box CO 5)
    - Miscellaneous letters, 1998-1999, 3 folders (Box CO 5)
    - Judy Hogan (Box CO 5)
    - Bob Moore, Locust Press (Box CO 5)
    - Miscellaneous business correspondence from editors and publishers, 3 folders (Box CO 5)
    - Meher Center controversy, 1995 (Box CO 5)
    - Kerry Johannsen (Box CO 5)
    - Dianna Henning (Box CO 5)
    - Bonnie McGrane Pirnie (Box CO 5)
    - Ted Pope (Box CO 5)
    - Nanna Nilson (Box CO 5)
    - Virginia Love Long (Box CO 5)
    - Moira Bailis (Box CO 5)
    - Bill Costley book manuscript (Box CO 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box CO 5)
    - Miscellaneous business correspondence, 2 folders (Box CO 6)
    - Dianna Henning, 13 folders (Box CO 6)
    - Celtic correspondence (Box CO 7)
      In addition to correspondence with Celtic authors, this subseries contains correspondence with poets in Bulgaria, Spain, and other countries. Also included is miscellaneous material from the Asheville Poetry Review (APR).
      - Anne MacLeod (Box CO 7)
      - Claudio Rodriguez Fer, Spain (Box CO 7)
      - Stuart Reid (?) photographs (Box CO 7)
      - Celtic countries and poets, 2 folders (Box CO 7)
      - Menna Elfyn (Box CO 7)
      - R. Gerallt Jones, Dewi Stephen Jones (Box CO 7)
      - Celtic poets, 4 folders (Box CO 7)
      - APR, Fall 1995/Winter 1996 issue, 4 folders (Box CO 7)
      - Dessislava Peteva (Box CO 7)
      - Crowe/Garlick and Celtic poets, 3 folders (Box CO 7)
      - Miscellaneous letters from editors, etc. (Box CO 7)
    - Miscellaneous letters, 3 folders (Box CO 8)
    - Letters from brother, D. Dawson, 3 folders (Box CO 8)
    - Miscellaneous letters, 1980s and 1993-1994, 3 folders (Box CO 8)
    - Letters from brother, D. Dawson, 2 folders (Box CO 8)
    - Miscellaneous letters, 3 folders (Box CO 8)
    - Miscellaneous personal correspondence, 1975-1992, 11 folders (Box CO 9)
    - Personal letters from loves and lovers, 11 folders (Box CO 9)
  - Writings
    - Early grade school writings (Box WR 1)
    - Later grade school writings (Box WR 1)
    - High school writings (Box WR 1)
    - Early grade school drawing (Box WR 1)
    - Early (first?) poem (Box WR 1)
    - Report on Rembrandt, 1965 (oversized) (Box WR 1)
    - Practical Epiphanies: Putting the Muse to Work, manuscript of artists' interviews, 1995 (Box WR 1)
    - A House of Girls: A Novel manuscript, 1999(?) (Box WR 1)
    - 10000 Dawns: The Love Poems of Yuan and Claire Goll manuscript, undated (Box WR 1)
    - The Fifth Rose and Other Love Poems, 1977-1981 (Box WR 1)
    - Water from the Moon, 1981-1986 (Box WR 1)
    - Edited copy of Water from the Moon, with commentary from Fred Chappell, 1989 (Box WR 1)
    - The Book of Rocks original manuscripts, 1992-1993 (?) (Box WR 1)
    - Poems to a Butterfly, 1977 (Box WR 1)
    - The Perfect Work, 1985(?) (Box WR 1)
    - Night Sun: An Initiation Trilogy, undated (contains The Personified Street, New Native, and Water from the Moon) (Box WR 1)
    - Writing the Wind: Poetry, 1985(?) (Box WR 1)
    - Learning to Dance: Selected Love Poem, 1974-1991 (Box WR 1)
    - Learning to Dance: various materials, 1985-1986 (related to publication of 1st part) (Box WR 1)
    - Pourquois je suis un monstre translation by Hughes-Alain Dal, 1977-1978 (Box WR 1)
    - Deep Language, 1985(?) (Box WR 1)
    - Rejected poems, undated (1970s?) (Box WR 1)
    - Poems from high school and college years, 1968-1972 and undated (Box WR 1)
    - Poems from France, 1973-1974 and undated (Box WR 1)
    - Le Livremeister: poems, 1973 (Box WR 1)
    - Dreams are Country Islands: poems, 1974-1975 (Box WR 1)
    - San Francisco poems, 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box WR 1)
    - Learning to Dance: Selected Love Poems, 1974-1976 (Box WR 2)
    - Columbus, part II (translation) by Irmgard Hierdeis (1991?) (Box WR 2)
    - Jubilee poems (Box WR 2)
    - College manuscripts, 1968-1972 (Box WR 2)
    - The Personified Street, original manuscript, 1977 (Box WR 2)
    - Personified Street, 1977 (Box WR 2)
    - Personified Street, photocopy (book 1) (Box WR 2)
    - The Laugharne Poems, 1995 (manuscript copy, uncorrected final draft) (Box WR 2)
    - Unedited poems, 1977-1981 and undated (from Fifth Rose?) (Box WR 2)
    - New Native: Poems, second draft (Box WR 2)
    - The Personified Street, corrected copy (Box WR 2)
    - Why I am a Monster (translation), corrected copy (Box WR 2)
    - Back to Sky Island: Early Poems, 1968-1972 (copies) (Box WR 2)
    - Saint Michael's Mountain/Le Livremeister: Paris poems, 1973 (copies) (Box WR 2)
    - Early San Francisco poems, 1974-1978 and undated, 2 folders (Box WR 2)
    - Street Poets' Press (poems published by the press), 1975 and undated (Box WR 2)
    - Early poems: No Such Thing as Prose (chapbook ms.), 1975, 1977 (Box WR 2)
    - Miscellaneous San Francisco poems (original typed ms.), 1974-1979 (Box WR 2)
    - Metamora: The Eyes of a Butterfly (program and text), 1987(?) (Box WR 2)
    - Notebook: introduction to anthology, 1970 (Box WR 2)
    - Notebook: courses, Spring 1971 (Box WR 2)
    - Notebook: World Prehistory course, undated (Box WR 2)
    - Miscellaneous poems, clippings, publicity for poetry slams (Box WR 2)
    - Original manuscript poems (originals, corrected drafts, typescripts, holographs, etc.) (Box WR 2)
    - Reviews, Interviews, Articles (Box WR 3)
      - Peter Greenaway, Prospero's Books. Green Line, 1992 Mar. (Box WR 3)
      - Hydrogen Jukebox, Spoleto Festival, 1990 (Box WR 3)
      - Spoleto Festival, 1994. Review in Point. (Box WR 3)
      - Philippe Genty. Review in Green Line, 1992 Aug. (Box WR 3)
      - Bob Dylan, Everything is Broken. Review in Point, 1993 June. (Box WR 3)
      - Laurie Anderson, Empty Places/Spoleto Festival, 1989. Review in Arts Journal. (Box WR 3)
      - Anne Dunn, Goddess. Review in Arts Journal, 1990 Apr. (Box WR 3)
      - Artists 4, Spoleto Festival, 1990. Review. (Box WR 3)
      - Rare Air in Concert review, 1989 (Box WR 3)
      - Paul Winter Consort (performance in Asheville, NC), 1989 Oct. Review in Arts Journal. (Box WR 3)
      - Anne Dunn, Orpheus (performance in Asheville, NC), 1993. Review in Out'n About, 1993. (Box WR 3)
      - Mark Olencki, Asheville Slam Poets show. Review in Green Line, 1993 Dec. (Box WR 3)
      - Philip Glass, Hydrogen Jukebox. Interview, 1990 (Box WR 3)
      - Spoleto Festival, 1992. Review in Green Line, 1992 July (Box WR 3)
      - Lady Smith Black Mambazo. Review, 1988 Nov. (Box WR 3)
      - Sacred Music/Sacred Dance. Review in Arts Journal, 1989 June (Box WR 3)
      - Interviews and articles in Katuah, 1984-1985 (Box WR 3)
      - Andrei Codrescu. Interview in Green Line, 1992 May (Box WR 3)
      - Interviews in Katuah, 1985 (Box WR 3)
      - Margie Gillis, Spoleto Festival, 1992. Review (Box WR 3)
      - King of Trains/Hub City Anthology. Review in Point, 1996 Apr. (Box WR 3)
      - Marilou Awiakta. Interview in Arts Journal, 1989 Sept. (Box WR 4)
      - Richard Lewis. Interview in Arts Journal (Box WR 4)
      - Eugene Friesen. Interview in Arts Journal, 1989 May (Box WR 4)
      - Ruth Zapohah. Review in Arts Journal, 1989 Sept. (Box WR 4)
      - Sally Hess. Interview in Arts Journal, 1988 Dec. (Box WR 4)
      - Jim Wayne Miller. Interview in Arts Journal, 1989 Aug. (Box WR 4)
      - Philip Glass, Les enfants terribles, Spoleto Festival, 1996. Interview by Crowe and Nan Watkins (Box WR 4)
      - Charles Lloyd. Interview in Jazz News, 1997 Holiday issue (Box WR 4)
      - Abdullah Ibrahim. Interview by Crowe and Nan Watkins in Jazz News, 1998 Sept/Oct. (Box WR 4)
      - Sathima Bea Benjamin. Cape Town Love. Review in Jazz News, Winter 1999 (Box WR 4)
      - Spoleto Festival, 1999. Article in Jazz News, Winter 1999 (Box WR 4)
      - Sathima Bea Benjamin. A Morning in Paris. Review in Jazz News, 1999 Holiday issue (Box WR 4)
      - Marijo Moore. Spirit Voices of Bones. Review in Wild Mountain Times, 1997 July (Box WR 4)
      - Ciaron Carson. Interview in WP Journal, 1996 June (Box WR 4)
      - Stoney Lamar. Review, 1989 Mar. (Box WR 4)
      - Christine Lassiter, Only the Dance. Review in Green Line, 1992 Dec. (Box WR 4)
      - Joy Harjo and Poetic Justice. Review in Jazz News, 1998 Mar./Apr. (Box WR 4)
      - Anthology of Magazine Verse & Yearbook of American Poetry/ed. by Alan F. Pater, 1985 (Box WR 4)
      - Anthology of Magazine Verse & Yearbook of American Poetry/ed. by Alan F. Pater, 1984 (Box WR 5)
      - Cherokee blood-degree ordinance controversy, article in Green Line, 1992 March (Box WR 5)
      - Georg Trakl, Autumn Sonata. Review in Arts Journal, 1990 Feb. (Box WR 5)
      - Jim Morrison, Wilderness. Review in Arts Journal, 1989 May (Box WR 5)
      - Gabriel Garcia Marquez, Love in the Time of Cholera. Review in Arts Journal, 1989 March (Box WR 5)
      - Howls, Raps and Roars. Review in Malaprops & Nexus, 1994 Fall (Box WR 5)
      - Janisse Ray, Ecology of a Cracker Childhood. Review in Rain Taxi (Box WR 5)
      - Leonard Cohen, Stranger Music. Review in Point, 1994 April (Box WR 5)
      - Snowbird Cherokees. Review in Green Lin, 1992 Feb. (Box WR 5)
      - Christopher Camuto, Another Country. Review in Now & Then, 1999 Summer (Box WR 5)
      - Gary Snyder Reader. Review in Rain Taxi, 1999 Fall (Box WR 5)
      - Merril Gilfillan, Burnt House to Paw Paw. Review in Rain Taxi, 1998 Spring (Box WR 5)
      - Barbara Duncan, ed., Living Stories of the Cherokee. Review in Mountain Xpress, 1998 Aug. (Box WR 5)
      - Maxine Hong Kingston, Tripmaster Monkey. Review in Arts Journal, 1989 Dec. (Box WR 5)
      - Wallace Fowlie, Rimbaud and Jim Morrison... Review in Asheville Poetry Review, 1995 Spring/Summer (Box WR 5)
      - Charles Lloyd. Interview for Jazz News, 1997 Holiday Issue (Box WR 5)
      - Peter Blue Cloud, Clans of Many Nations. Review in Wild Mountain Times, 1997 Winter (Box WR 5)
      - Peter Coyote, Sleeping Where I Fall. Review in Rain Taxi, 1998 Summer (Box WR 5)
      - Jello Biafra, If Evolution is Outlawed. Review in Rain Taxi, 1999 Apr. (Box WR 5)
      - Marilou Awiakta, Selu: Seeking the Corn Mother's Wisdom. Review by Crowe and Nan Watkins in Green Line, 1994 Jan. (Box WR 5)
      - "Millennial Make-over: Sylva's New Look," article in Mountain Xpress, 1994 Oct. 12 (Box WR 5)
      - John Lane, As the World Around Us Sleeps; Sharon Doubiago, South America Mi Hija. Review in Green Line, 1992 Oct. (Box WR 5)
      - "The Blue Wall: Update 1998," article in Wild Mountain Times, 1998 Mar/Apr. (Box WR 5)
      - "Over the Ditch: the Return of the Ram," article in Sun Magazine, 1986 Mar. (Box WR 5)
      - Gary Snyder, Mountains and Rivers without End. Review in Wild Mountain Times, 1996 Fall (Box WR 5)
  - Legal Materials (Box WR 5)
    - Miscellaneous official documents (one packet) (Box WR 5)
    - Papers relating to lawsuit brought by Crowe against NC Arts Journal (Box WR 5)
  - Journals, Calendars, and Class Notes (Box J 1)
    - Journals (Box J 1)
      1978 June; 1980, Jan.; 1985; Scotland journal, 1995; Also the Astro, undated; I; II; Farm, Indiana, undated; California/SF poems, undated; San Francisco, 1974; unlabelled (3 volumes); Deep Language, I. Moon Cycle, undated; Portions of Whole Thoughts - San Francisco poems, undated; Wales/Laugharne journals/original poems, 1993 and 1995.
    - Calendars, 1976-1999 (Box J 1)
    - Class notes, Tuesday sessions with Harold Norse; Russian (Box J 1)
  - San Francisco Period (Box SF 1)
    - The Grant Getter's Gazette, published by Beatitude, 1976 (Box SF 1)
    - Misc. poems and rejection notices (Box SF 1)
    - "Friday night class" with Harold Norse, 1975 (Box SF 1)
    - Readings, promotional projects, Beatitude editorship (Box SF 1)
    - Proposition 15: Reading-rally Union Square, 1976 29 May (Box SF 1)
    - Beatitude #25 (original manuscript), 1976 (Box SF 1)
    - Philip Suntree/Thomas, Poetry Consumer/Releve Press/Beatitude, 1977 (envelope) (Box SF 1)
    - Ballet Poems, mss. for Turkey Press Books, undated (Box SF 1)
    - Beatitude #23, 1976 Feb. (Box SF 1)
    - Beatitude readings, Little Fox Theatre, 1976 Feb. 9 (Box SF 1)
    - Beatitude book #2, Jack Hirschman, undated (Box SF 1)
    - Neeli Cherkovski pub. by Thomas Crowe (Dawson), Beatitude Press books and broadsides; Public Notice (book); Notes from Syropa (broadside); The Be-Attitude (broadside) (Box SF 1)
    - Opening of the Sky, Ken Wainio; The Poet, David Dawson; Releve Press broadsheet, 1977 Dec. (Box SF 1)
  - Printed Materials (Box PR 1)
    Dates for serial publications indicate range of years and do not indicate issue dates or volume numbers. Some serial runs are complete; others are not.
    - Agayuli, 1981 (Box PR 1)
    - Oyster Bay Review, 1997-1998 (Box PR 1)
    - The Journal, 1994-1996 (Box PR 1)
    - The Cuirt Journal, 1995, 1999 (Box PR 1)
    - Bullhead, 1994-1995 (Box PR 1)
    - North River Review, 1995, 1998 (Box PR 1)
    - Waters, 1976, 1977 (Box PR 1)
    - Pine Mountain Sand & Gravel, 1997, 1998 (Box PR 1)
    - Quality Living, 1989, 1990 (Box PR 1)
    - Southern Appalachian Resource Catalog, 1980, 1981 (Box PR 1)
    - Oxygen, 1995-1996 (Box PR 1)
    - Resurgence, 1999 (Box PR 1)
    - Now & Then, 1996, 1998-1999 (Box PR 1)
    - Rain Taxi, 1996-2000 (Box PR 1)
    - RFD: A Country Journal for Gay Men Everywhere, 1986-1988 (Box PR 1)
    - Nexus, 1990, 1994-1998 (Box PR 1)
    - Cold Drill, 1991 (Box PR 1)
    - Amerus, 1979 (Box PR 1)
    - North Carolina Literary Review, 1995 (Box PR 1)
    - Argus, 1996-1998 (Box PR 1)
    - Miscellaneous journals (8 folders) (Box PR 2)
    - Beatitude, 1975-1976 (Box PR 2)
    - Asheville Poetry Review, 1994-1996, 1998-1999 (Box PR 2)
    - Books (Box PR 2)
      Writing on Glass: Essays, Interviews, Criticism (1997); Directory of American Poetry Books (1994); The Many Faces of Appalachia (1985); Writing Work: Writers on Working-Class Writing (1999); Blue Ridge Parkway: Agent of Transition (1986).
    - Books (Box PR 3)
      Interviewing Appalachia: The Appalachian Journal Interviews, 1978-1992 (1994); Coffeehouse Poetry Anthology (1996); Watching the River Flow: A Century in Irish Poetry (1999); Building Great Sheds (1999).
  - New Native Press Records (Box NNP 1)
    - Chapbooks (Box NNP 1)
      - Two Lives, Ken Wainio (2 folders) (Box NNP 1)
      - Deep Language, Thomas Crowe (2 folders) (Box NNP 1)
      - 7 Headed Sewing Machine, Katalin Ladik (2 folders) (Box NNP 1)
      - Body Poems, John Lane (Box NNP 1)
      - The Perfect Work, Thomas Crowe (Box NNP 1)
      - Why I am a Monster, trans. Thomas Crowe (Box NNP 1)
      - You Must Go Home Again, Thomas Crowe (see also, Oversize series) (Box NNP 1)
      - The Snow Has No Voice, John Smelcer (Box NNP 1)
    - Drafts and Proofs (Box NNP 1)
      - Poems for Che Guevara's Dream (Box NNP 1)
      - Encyclopedia of Native American Tribes (Box NNP 1)
      - The Laugharne Poems (Box NNP 1)
      - In Wineseller's Street, Hafiz (Box NNP 1)
      - Night Sun (Box NNP 2)
        Includes materials for The Personified Street, New Native, and Water from the Moon.
      - Against Information production materials (Box NNP 2)
      - Writing the Wind (Box NNP 3)
        Includes correspondence, drafts and proofs, typesetting, and some corrections.
      - Writing the Wind (Box NNP 4)
        Includes manuscripts, notes, corrections, publicity, and reviews.
      - Writing the Wind (Box NNP 5)
        Includes corrections, designs, and other proof materials.
      - New Native Press letterhead, stationary, catalogs, etc. (Box NNP 5)
      - Seizures of the Sun (Box NNP 5)
        Includes correspondence, originals, manuscripts, proofs, laser-set texts, etc. Some materials removed to Oversize series.
      - Starfuck (Box NNP 5)
        Many files transferred to electronic records server. Also includes copies of extracts, drafts, etc.
      - Celtic Blood (Box NNP 5)
        Includes typeset proofs, typescript, and covers.
      - Celtic Blood (Box NNP 6)
        Includes correspondence, clippings, reviews, proofs.
    - Unpublished submissions (Box NNP 6)
    - Final publications (Box NNP 6)